Hello, everyone. Welcome to
our last lecture together.
If you don't remember me,
my name is Dr. Ermin Tala,
and I'm an internal medicine
PGY1 at Jacoby Einstein.
In the past three
lectures, we explored the
physiology behind the
ECG, then an approach to
reading an ECG, where we
took a brief visit with
Ryan Reynolds. For most
of us, that may be the
only visit we get with
him, but you never know.
And then we discussed
a bunch of arrhythmias
that you probably
don't remember.
Lastly, we'll discuss
a few nuances that
we can find on the
EKG and how this may
alter your management
as a physician.
We'll start with
an extremely high
-yield topic you
are likely, if not
definitely, to see
on Comlex and USMLE,
the AV blocks.
So here are the session
objectives. As always,
if you can answer these
in your own words,
then you're probably in
a good spot. I've also
included the corresponding
page in first aid
if you're using it as a
supplemental resource.
Now, before we begin, I do
want to clarify one thing.
You may see the term
heart block or AV block on
an exam or in a textbook.
I do want to clarify that
these mean exactly the same
thing. They are the same
thing, and they're exactly
what they sound like,
a slowing or blocking of
conduction at the AV node.
Now, just a reminder,
the AV node is
what separates the
timing of contractions
between the atria
and ventricles.
Now there are four types of
AV blocks that we need to
know of. A first degree is
the least severe, a third
degree is the most severe,
and because medicine is
annoying, there are two types
of second degree blocks.
In terms of management,
the first two AV blocks,
first degree and MOBIS type
1 are pretty asymptomatic
or benign, usually not
requiring much treatment.
Second degree type 2 and
third degree heart block
usually present with
symptomatically and are managed with
the pacemaker. Now before we
begin, I want to introduce
you guys to the heart
block poem. Maybe you've
heard of it, maybe you
haven't, but it's an extremely
helpful tool we can use to
help learn the heart blocks.
So let's read it through.
If the R is far from the P,
then you have a first degree.
P-R gets longer, longer,
longer a drop, it's
a case of *****-bock.
If some R's don't get
through, prepare to
pace that mobit's two.
If the R's and P's don't agree,
prepare to pace
that third degree.
This poem goes in
order from first degree
and makes our way
down to third degree,
again going from least to
most severe, and can be
extremely useful when
learning the heart blocks.
We'll reference
back to it as we
progress throughout
the lecture.
Now let's begin
with the first type
of heart block, first
degree AV block.
But before we do that, ask
yourself this question.
What interval on the EKG
defines the time difference
between the atria and
ventricular contraction?
Well, I can't hear you,
so I can't really confirm
if you're right or wrong,
but it's the PR interval.
Feel free to celebrate if
you got that one right.
The P wave represents
atrial contraction, and the
QRS complex represents
ventricular contraction.
Now, a first-degree
heart block, which is
the least severe of
heart blocks, affects,
as we mentioned
before, the AV node,
which is now going
to be defined
simply by a prolonged
PR interval.
What's a normal PR
interval? Less than 0.2
seconds, or one big
box or five tiny boxes.
Everything else in the
rhythm strip is normal.
Of course, this is
usually asymptomatic,
and no treatment is required.
Back to our poem.
For first degree, if
the R is far from the
P, then you have a
first degree. So our PR
interval is the only
thing that's affected,
and it's prolonged
and the least severe.
Reason why first degree
is highlighted in green.
Now, we'll begin to look at
our second degree AV blocks.
Give the poem a
read and see if you
can figure out
what the defining
features of second
degree AV blocks are.
so now we'll talk about
the second degree heart
block starting with type
1 unfortunately second
degree type 1 does go by
a few names second degree
type 1 second degree mobile
type 1 and even *****
block unfortunately you
will have to commit all
these names to memory so
better off just starting from
now similarly to first
degree heart block the
block occurs at the av
node so like we saw first
degree heart block where
the PR interval was affected
and prolonged, we have
a similar pattern here.
So since the AV node
is being blocked,
we're going to
have, or see on an
EKG, a prolongation
of the PR interval.
However, different from
first degree heart block,
we're going to see a
progressive prolongation of
the PR interval. While in
first degree heart block,
the PR interval was
prolonged, it was fixed. In
this case, however, we're
going to get a progressive
prolongation of the PR
interval. So if we turn
our attention to the
rhythm strip on the bottom,
we can look at our
first PR interval
right here. That
looks pretty normal.
We go to our second.
Looks a bit different from the
first one. It looks prolonged.
When we go to the third
PR interval, it looks
even more different from
the second and the first
PR intervals. It's even
more prolonged until
finally we get to this
lonely P wave with no
QRS complex following
it. This is what we call
a drop B or a non-conducted
P-wave, meaning that
there's no QRS complex
following the P-wave.
So in a second-degree
mode with type 1,
we get prolongation
of the PR interval
progressively.
So each PR interval becomes
longer and longer and
longer until finally we
have a drop B, meaning we
don't have the QRS complex
following that P-wave.
The cycle just repeats
over and over, and it's
regularly irregular,
something to keep in mind.
Treatment is usually
not indicated, as
this rhythm is
usually asymptomatic.
So now, if we refer back
to our heart block poem, if
we go to second degree type
1, we see PR gets longer,
longer, longer drop. It's a
case of Wankybock. So it may
be useful to commit or
associate the name Winkybock
with second degree type 1,
especially in relation to the
poem. It can help you remember
what EKG findings you'll
see. So like we see here,
we have the PR interval.
That's getting
progressively prolonged,
prolonged, prolonged,
right? So PR gets longer,
longer, longer, drop.
We have a Winkybock.
kind of silly but it's
an easy and fun way
to commit it and keep
it in your memory so
next up we have a second
degree mobitz type 2 so in
this case second degree
type 2 is similar to second
degree type 1 except the
drop p wave is after a bunch
of consistent pr intervals
now what I mean by this
is that there's no
increasingly prolonging of the
pr interval so while we
saw that in mobitz type 1
there was progressive
prolongation if we look at the
rhythm shift on the bottom
here we see the PR interval
is pretty constant until
we see a lonely P wave
and then PR interval
constant constant etc second
degree type 2 AV blocks are
more symptomatic they're
more severe and they're
treated with pacemakers because
the drop beat can cause and
will cause a bradycardia
like we said the patients
will be symptomatic
and they can develop symptoms
of low cardiac output,
be it presyncope, syncope,
fatigue, and
shortness of breath.
A pacemaker, which we
will speak about in a few
slides, is a treatment of
choice because it literally
paces the ventricles
and their contractions.
One thing to note
too is now we're
moving lower down in
the heart's anatomy.
So So it won't be
uncommon to see widening
of the QRS complex.
Not always, but you
can see it. Something
to keep in mind.
Now, back to our poem,
the Heartblock poem.
So if we go to
second degree type 2,
it reads, If some R's don't get
through, prepare to
pace them. Mobitz 2.
So, like we said,
pure interval,
pure interval, pure
interval, finally a drop
beat. PR intervals aren't
getting progressively
longer. They're pretty
much, they can be normal or
prolonged, but that
duration of the PR interval
doesn't change until
finally we have a drop B.
So now back to our
heart block poem. If we
find second degree type
two, which is highlighted
in yellow, right?
Because we're increasing
in our severity within
these heart blocks.
Our poem reads, if some R's
don't get through, prepare
to paste that mode with two.
So again, we have our PR
interval that is either that
is fixed it can be normal
or fixed prolonged until
finally we have a drop b so
let me just highlight this
here again so we have our
PR interval here PR interval
here PR interval here and
finally again a dropped QRS
complex so no QRS complex
after this p wave so again
PR interval is fixed until
finally we have a dropped
QRS complex and And again,
prepare to pace that MOBIT
type 2, cluing you into what
the treatment is for MOBIT
type 2 pace, aka pacemaker.
So now let's talk about third
degree or complete heart block.
Like the name
suggests, there is
complete block or
complete dissociation
between the atria
and the ventricles.
What do we mean by
this? Well, basically,
if we were to take a
look here at our rhythm
strip, we have, and
we can see, P waves.
and also some QRS complexes.
If we look at the
rhythm strip, we
can see that there
are more P waves than
QRS complexes,
right, if we count.
And what we also notice is
that after the P waves, some
of them have QRS complexes
following them, but others
don't. This is what we mean
by complete dissociation.
Basically, the atria and
ventricles are pacing at their
own rate. So we're going
to get P waves that aren't
conducted, meaning there's
no QRS complex after them.
And the reason why
there's more P waves is
because the atrial pacing
is greater than ventricular
pacing. So we're going
to get more P waves
and less QRS complexes,
and we're going to have
some P waves without QRS
complexes after them.
Some of the defining
features of complete heart
block is equal PP intervals
and equal RR intervals.
What do we mean by that?
If we were to count the
distance between P waves,
it would be constant.
Similarly, if we count
the distances between the
consecutive QRS complexes,
it will also be constant.
You can even try this
on your own. If you take
your point fingers on
both hands and you put
your left on one P wave,
the first P wave, and
your right index finger
on the second p wave
you can then maintain
maintaining that distance
move your fingers
throughout the rhythm
strip and see that your
fingers are lining up
exactly or constantly within
each consecutive p wave
similarly you can do the
same thing for the qrs
complex but again this
is a defining feature and
something I just wanted to
point out to you guys um
another thing to note too
right since we're in uh his
purkinje system territory
right because the block
is occurring within the
his purkinje system we can
also have changes in the
qrs complex morphology right
because when if we're in
ventricle ventricle area
depolarization may also
be affected so we can
have what's called
widening of the qrs complex
there are many causes of
third degree or complete
heart block so it's
important to figure out the
underlying cause because
there are some causes
like Lyme disease for example
that can cause or lead
to heart block specifically
third degree heart
block but could be a
treatable or preventable
cause but in general for
third degree heart block
for our cases and purposes
your treatment will be
with a pacemaker because
it will pace the heart.
This here is an EKG
of a third degree
complete heart block.
Again, we can see the P
waves beating at their
own rate, but also
spaced pretty evenly
apart from each other.
Same thing with
the QRS complexes.
Again, beating at
their own rate, but
spaced relatively
equal to each other. So
equal PP intervals
equal r intervals.
What I also wanted to
note, well, want to note to
you guys as well is, like
I mentioned, we're in
ventricle territory. So
the QRS complex can get
affected. If we look at
V1, excuse me, lead one, we
see that this QRS complex
here is prolonged, right?
Because we're in ventricle
areas. QRS complex is
also representation of
ventricular depolarization.
Similarly, we have
an inverted T-wave,
again, ventricular
repolarization.
So what I'm trying
to do is, again,
relate normal physiology
to some of the
findings that we'll
see on the EKG.
So this I kind of
put here for fun,
especially for those
who are interested
in cardiology,
just like myself.
So obviously, you won't be
tested on this slide, but
it may help you with
visualization how the pacemakers
work how they're placed
there's a bunch of different
options for pacemakers
different indications where
basically they act like either
the atria or the ventricles
so to bring this all together
here's a summary of all
the av blocks so on the left
here I included the sites
of where the blocks are
occurring rhythm strips
representing what you would
see in each respective block
as well as the correlation
to the heart poem. All right
so take some time to go
over the slide I think this
is probably one of the more
helpful slides within the
lecture and pretty much a
good summary of what to look
for within the blocks where
the blocks are occurring
and again our poem to help
us remember our finding
ECG findings with respect
to each of the blocks.
Before we continue,
let's briefly
review the cardiac
conduction system.
The electricity in the
heart flows from the
SA node to the AV node.
After, it flows down
the bundle of hiss into
the left and right bundle
branches, finally
ending at the Purkinje
fibers which can then
contract the ventricles.
If the bundle branches are
blocked, it wouldn't be
too surprising to see
that the ventricles would
be affected. On an ECG,
this can show up as changes
in the QRS complex, since
the ventricles would now
take longer to fully
depolarize. Keep this in mind
as we continue and begin
our discussion on bundle
branch blocks. So before
we begin talking about
bundle branch blocks, I
do want to say one thing.
I wouldn't go too hard
remembering or trying to learn
all the behind-the-scenes
information regarding them,
because in general, it is
a lower-yield topic for the
boards, but it's pretty
interesting or cool to learn
about, especially being able
to identify them, especially
as you progress during
your career, during your
third-year clinical rotations,
as well as a physician.
So again, don't get too
caught up in the details.
What you will be responsible
for is being able
to identify a right or
left bundle branch block.
I'll make sure to highlight
when something else is
relevant, but if you can
diagnose or identify left and
right bundle branch blocks,
then you're in a good spot.
So general principle that
I want to bring up before
we discuss the more
specific ECG findings, the
ventricular septum itself is
usually activated from left
to right. What this means
is that the left bundle
branch fires at a slightly
faster rate than the right.
You can think about this
in the terms that the heart
and brain's blood supply
comes from the left side,
so it's a more important
side compared to the right.
Now in the left bundle
branch block, there's an
issue with conductance on
the left bundle branch, hence
left bundle branch block.
This means that the
direction of septal
depolarization becomes reversed.
So in a left bundle
branch block, we
have a septal
depolarization that goes
through the right,
then to the left.
The QRS represents
what on the ECG?
Yep, depolarization,
specifically ventricular
depolarization. So
something that we've
touched already is that
the QRS complex would
be prolonged, right?
Because we're in
ventricular area. So beyond
the three tiny boxes
or 120 milliseconds,
we therefore have an
issue in conductance
in the ventricles. So
the normal QRS will
be disrupted in some
way, shape or form.
Now V1. So if we look
back and think about the
locations of the actual
electrodes of the ECG, lead
V1 is to the right of the
heart and V6 is on the
opposite, the left side
of the heart. If the left
bundle branch is blocked,
the right will depolarize
normally, then it will
spread to the left. And
again, quick reminder,
depolarization towards induces
a positive deflection,
and depolarization away
induces a negative inflection.
So as depolarization
goes to the left ventricle,
we see on the ECG a
winding of the QRS in V1
with a more negative QRS.
I do also want to mention,
so the overall direction
of depolarization from right
to left produces a tall
R-wave in the lateral
leads, be it lead 1, V5, and
6, and deep S-waves in the
right precordial leads,
V1 to V3, and usually leads
to left-axis deviation.
So here we can see a left
bundle branch block on a
12-lead ECG. What we
see, we see a widened QRS
complex, which we anticipated
would happen, with a
negative inflection in V1,
like we spoke about just
before and we can see that
in v1 clearly with the
widening of the qrs complex
with like we mentioned a
negative inflection right
so the qrs complex pointing
down as well as the changes
we mentioned in v5 with
um prolonged qrs complex
and a deep tall s wave as
we mentioned before we're
in ventricular area so
the qrs complex is going
to be affected and like we
see here prolonged. So we
have a wide QRS complex
we can see in both V1 and
V5 and we have and we can
appreciate the deep S wave
in V1 as well as the tall
or peaked R wave in the
V5 or the lateral leads.
Now why would a bundle
branch block in general be
clinically relevant? Well
causes of a bundle branch
block is although something
we skipped over earlier is
an important finding especially
if it's a new finding
on an EKG. So in a patient
that develops let's say
a new left bundle branch
block and you compare the
ECG you're looking at to
an old ECG that didn't show
that bundle branch block
it should start to clue you
in into a MI or heart
attack which is an important
thing that we don't want
to miss and keep in our
differential. So nuance that
left bundle branch block
could be an MI happening
right in front of your eyes.
So, there are a lot of
very cool EP specifics when
it comes to bundle branch
blocks, but if you're
interested in cardiology,
you'll learn that and
be more exposed to it
during fellowship training.
At this point, we can
just look at a cute
bunny named Roger from
Melville, New York.
Whenever you think of
right bundle, think of our
bunny Roger. Right bundle,
Roger the rabbit. it.
Now, Roger has bunny
ears. And the way you're
going to remember a
right bundle branch block
is by identifying the
pattern RSR prime in V1.
So in this case, why is he
relevant to our conversation
is because it follows a
bunny-like orientation.
So this RSR prime pattern,
so this be The R, S,
R' pattern is said to
resemble a set of bunny ears.
Personally, I've never
seen it really this way,
but if it helps you, then
remember it that way.
It also can be represented
by the letter M, which we
kind of see in the orientation
that we had drawn here.
in the rsr prime pattern
so whichever way helps you
remember it stick to that way
but again rsr prime pattern
that we'll see specifically
in lead v1 and we'll
see in the lateral leads
some deep s waves with some
greater duration in the r
wave so one thing I do want
to mention if we think back
to the lead placements on
a v of an ekg so v1 is to
the right of the harp and v6
is on the opposite side,
the left side of the heart.
If there's a right bundle
branch block, the left
ventricle depolarizes
normally. Then it'll spread
to the right. As the
polarization goes to the
right ventricle, we'll see
on the ECG a widening of
the QRS complex in V1
with a more positive QRS.
Another thing I do
want to mention too
is if we kind of just
think about this,
the right bundle branch
covers the right side
of the heart, so the
right ventricle. If we
reference the ECG setup,
like we said, we know that
V1 and V2 are the leads
right over the right
side of the heart. So
we'll see changes evident
there. Similarly, in
the left bundle branch
block, we'll also see
changes in the V5 and V6.
So I do want to mention one
thing. If we relate back
to the lead placement of
an EKG when performing an
EKG, we remember that V1
is placed on the right side
of the heart and V6 on the
opposite side, the left
side of the heart. Now, if
the right bundle branch is
blocked, the left ventricle
would depolarize normally,
then it'll spread to the
right. As the polarization
goes to the right ventricle,
we'll see on the ECG a
widening of the QRS in V1
with a more positive QRS.
The right bundle branch,
like we just said, covers
the right side of the
heart, aka right ventricle.
So thinking back to the
ECG setup, V1 and V2
are the leads placed
right over the right side
of the heart, so we should
see ECG changes there.
So here's a 12-lead ECG
with a wide QRS and RSR
prime pattern or bunny
ear pattern in V1 and V2.
There's also So
correlation with
the right side of the heart,
so V1 and V2, ECG changes,
and again, our bunny ears,
our R-S-R prime pattern,
our R-S-R prime pattern.
You may be asking,
hey, why is the T
-wave inverted in V1
as well as in V2?
Well, if we think about it,
what does the T-wave represent?
Ventricular depolarization.
So, excuse me,
repolarization. So if there's
an issue with ventricular
depolarization, it
wouldn't be hard to imagine
or assume that there
would be changes and
issues with ventricular
repolarization, which
is why we can also see
inverted T-waves or changes
in T-wave morphology.
If that was overwhelming
or confusing, there is
an easier way of identifying
bundle branch blocks,
and for our purposes, we
only need V1 to do so.
This is termed the
turn signal theory.
Now, imagine you're
walking from the T-wave
to the QRS complex,
moving right to left.
If you turn to
the left, then you
have a left bundle
branch block.
The QRS will be more
negative in inflection.
But if you turn to the
right, then you have a right
bundle branch block, and the
QRS will be more positive.
The requirements for this,
be it bundle branch blocks
in general, is that we
have a QRS duration greater
than 120 milliseconds and
utilizing, again, lead V1.
so to illustrate that
let's look at our
lead one here so if
we were driving a car
or walking we'd start
from the right and
move to the left so
moving from the right
if we continue on our
pathway here we'll
see that we have no
choice but to go right
versus if we were to start
on this complex here start
from the right move towards
the left we have no choice
but to move down to the
left so based off of the
direction that we moved starting
from right to left that'll
dictate what kind of bundle
branch it is so since we
had to move right here this
is a right bundle branch
block and if we since we had
to move our direction towards
the left here, this is a
left bundle branch block.
So now let's shift
the conversation.
Want to talk
electrolyte services?
Okay.
As you can tell, we're
going to first start by
talking about potassium.
But before we do that, when
it comes to electrolytes,
we can have a lot of
electrolytes or a low
concentration of electrolytes.
Now I want to clue you guys
into a general paradigm
that we can use that works
about 90% of the time when it
comes to electrolyte
concentrations and ECG changes.
About 97% of the time,
again, this works. So
when we have a high
electrolyte concentration,
like in hyperkalemia
or hypercalcemia, two
things that we can note
and look for are QT and
QRS changes. Specifically,
we will get widening
of the QRS complex and
a short QT interval.
On the flip side, we would
expect the reverse. When
we have a low electrolyte
concentration like
hypokalemia and hypocalcemia,
we would expect a prolonged
QT interval and a shorter
QRS complex duration.
Again, this is a general
rule to keep in mind. It
can help make it easier
to learn some of the ECG
changes when it comes to
electrolyte disturbances. It
works, again, about 90%
of the time. So keep this
in mind as you review, as
you go through ECGs with
electrolyte anomalies.
It can make it easier
for you to kind of group
all the ECG changes and
make it a little bit
easier to understand and
have less to memorize
if we group changes in
electrolytes based off
of groups and grouping.
So as we mentioned, why
do we want to talk about
electrolytes in general?
Well, when we have
electrolyte disturbances,
we're going to worry about
the heart. And potassium
is one of the big ions
that we want to worry
about electrolytes. So with
potassium, as we mentioned,
going back to our
general paradigm, what
we can expect to see when
there's high potassium
is, on the ECG, is QT
interval shortening and
winding of the QRS complex.
One thing that we do want
to note that's pretty
specific for very high
potassium is tall, peak, narrow
T waves. Now, one way to
think about this or remember
this is to remember that
K, or potassium limbs
lives under the T wave so
with hyperkalemia we get
spiked or peaked T waves
and by peaked we mean T wave
amplitude that's bigger than
the QRS complex amplitude
so this is a pretty high
yield ECG findings to
know of especially because
it's specific to hyperkalemia
so knowing this is going
to be important on exams
and on boards and again
in clinical practice
especially because this is
one of the first things you'll
see with an elevated
potassium level, is the tall
peaked T waves. As the
concentration continues to
increase, then we see further
ECG changes. But again,
for our level, we mostly
want to, and for boards,
we mostly want to think of
tall peaked T waves being
representative and
associated with hyperkalemia.
So if we get peak T-waves
and hyperkalemia, then we
must get flattened or shallow
T-waves and hypokalemia.
Now, it may even get to
the level of dragging
down the ST segment
if severe enough.
One pretty vital or
important thing for us to
know about is another
wave called the U-wave.
As you can imagine, in
the alphabet, the letter U
comes after T, so it's not
hard to see that it is another
inflection in the ECG that
comes after the U-wave.
The U-wave itself
represents repolarization of
Purkinje fibers and it's
always there in the ECG but
it's usually so small
that we can't really tell.
Now for this reason
again super high yield
for us to recognize
shallow T waves with
a U wave is characteristic
of hypokalemia.
A way to remember this
is substituting the
O in hypokalemia with
U or hypokalemia.
The reason why we care
about low electrolytes
like potassium is that,
as we mentioned before,
prolongation of the QT
interval, which if we
remember it to our
prior lectures, can
induce torsades de point,
which can be lethal.
Now, on to calcium.
Again, as we mentioned before,
one of the things that
we can see with increased
electrolyte concentration
would be QT interval
shortening, which is
one of the hallmarks of
hypercalcemia.
Hypercalcemia in itself
has a ton of different
causes. In our conversation,
we just want to fixate
and look at what it would
look like on an ECG.
Obviously, you're not
going to look at an
ECG to find the cause.
This is where blood
tests like a BMP, CMP,
which are basic or
comprehensive metabolic
panels come into play.
So again, just
for hypercalcemia,
QT interval shortening
is pretty much
the hallmark of what
we're going to see.
So when it comes to
calcium, the more imminently
dangerous of the
calcaemias for the heart is
hypocalcemia. As we mentioned
before, in hypocalcemia
and in general,
following our general
paradigm, when we have
a low concentration of
electrolytes, we're likely
to see QT interval changes,
specifically prolongation
of the QT interval.
Now, this may be
problematic because we all
know that a prolonged
QT interval redisposes
us to something. And
what is that condition?
Right, torsades de point.
Hypocalcemia, hypokalemia,
and hypomagnesemia can
actually cause QT prolongation,
which can lead to torsades.
This is pretty high yield
to know, specifically the
electrolytes. And it can
also help us remember the
association between low
electrolyte, QT prolongation,
and torsades de point.
So again, establishing
and grouping
similarities like low
electrolyte concentrations
and ECG changes are
pretty helpful and
something you should
definitely be aware of.
So this is kind of a random
thing to throw in here.
Obviously, hypothermia
is not an electrolyte
disturbance, but it does
cause a characteristic wave
that we get to know of
called an Osborne or J-wave.
It's important to know
both names. I've seen
it referred to as
Osborne wave or J-wave on
exams. so just commit
it to memory from now.
The J wave is also known as
the Camelholm sign, which
maybe it helps you remember
the kind of morphology
that it gives. So again,
just going back to the normal
EKG, we have our QRS complex
followed by the T wave.
This point here
at the end of the QRS complex
is referred to as a J point.
what we can get especially
when it comes to hypothermia
is what's called j-point
elevation so we have
our normal QRS complex here
followed by an upsloping
of the j-point so
where it was nice
and fixed in our
first schematic here
highlighted in red, we
don't really see that in our
bottom drawing, nor do we
see that on the actual EKG.
So just to give you
guys some information on
what the J-point is
and how it's related to
Osborne waves. So part
of the reason why it
gets the name J-waves
is J-point elevation.
And again, remember
the other name as well,
because we don't want
to lose points on exams,
especially on the
NBMEs and Comlex.
So here's a summary slide
of what we spoke about.
Again if you can remember
our general paradigm as
well as some of the specifics
when it comes to the
electrolyte disturbances
should be in a good place.
So here are two more
pathologies that
are relevant to clinical
practice. They're
not too relevant
for exams on ECG.
Feel free to take what you
want from these next slides.
They'll definitely help
you though when you're
suspicious on some odd ECGs
with a symptomatic patient.
So I'm not going to
jump into LVH or left
ventricular hypertrophy
too much, but what
we need to know is
that in ventricular
hypertrophy we get,
like the name suggests,
thickening of the ventricles.
This can be seen usually
from chronic hypertension
or high blood pressure.
Now the thickening of the
myocardial fibers when it
comes to hypertrophy occurs
in a parallel fashion.
This is in contrast to
dilated cardiomyopathy where
the heart is expanding
in series. Now we put a
series and parallel circuit
schematic here. I hope it's
not too triggering but
it's a good way to think
about how the sarcomeres
are added be it in series
or parallel and how it would
affect the heart. So in
LVH we get thickening of
the actual ventricular
wall versus in dilated
cardiomyopathy where we get
kind of widening or enlargement
of the heart but not
the thickening of the
ventricles that we see here.
In terms of LVH on the
ECG, we see an increased
amplitude in the curious
complexes throughout the EKG.
When it comes to precordial
leads, so there are
specific criteria. There's
a so-called Lyon criteria,
there's a Cornell criteria
but for our cases and
purposes just to be able to
recognize it what we can look
for especially in the
precordial leads is at the
QRS amplitude now when
we're suspecting ventricular
hypertrophy specifically in
the precordial leads we're
looking for a QRS amplitude
of at least two big
boxes so lead two kind of
illustrates that pretty well
for us excuse me lead three
so we have a QRS complex
amplitude here of almost
about three big boxes.
Even lead two here on
the rhythm strip, we're
kind of borderline
two big boxes, so it's
cluing us into some
ventricular hypertrophy.
When it comes to the precordial
leads, V1 to V6, good
rule of thumb to recognize
hypertrophy, ventricular
hypertrophy, is a QRS
amplitude of at least five big
boxes. So if we start here,
we get about half a box,
one big box, two big box,
three big box, four big
boxes, so about four and a
half big boxes in amplitude.
V2 probably illustrates
this a lot better, and also
V3, where if we start from
the QRS amplitude here,
we're getting one big box,
two, three, four, five
six seven eight so we've
fulfilled this criteria
especially within the picordial
leads especially v2 and
v3 so good rule of thumb
there are criteria which
you can also look up there
are specific volt amplitudes
between leads where you
can get the summation of
those and it'll clue you
in and fulfill one of the
criterias for lvh but a
good rule of thumb if your
QRS amplitude in the limb
leads is greater than two
big boxes, that's kind of
the precordial criteria
that you're meeting. And
if you have a QRS amplitude
in the precordial leads
that is greater than five
big boxes, you're kind of
fulfilling the precordial
ventricular hypertrophy
criteria in that
sense. So two big boxes
in the limb leads,
five big boxes in
the precordial leads.
So we spoke about issues
at the AV node, which
are more common than
what we're going to
speak about now, which
is called sick sinus
syndrome, where there's
a problem at the SA node.
Now, sick sinus
syndrome occurs from
a lot of different
reasons, but it's
most commonly caused
by advanced age.
The symptoms are
the same as any
other pathologic bradycardia,
so dizziness,
presyncope, syncope,
shortness of
breath, and fatigue.
You can treat this
condition with a pacemaker.
so that concludes
our fourth and final
lecture in the clinical
cardiology series
hope you found these
lectures to be valuable
to your learning and I
appreciate any feedback
feel free to email me or
any of the senior members of
the research team if you
have any questions also join
us on mondays from 12 to 1
eastern standard time over
zoom to review ecgs for
more exposure I know in the
beginning especially with
ecgs it can be a pretty
daunting task so I hope I was
able to make ecg reading a
bit more attainable and
increase your confidence and
again as always make sure to
take some time for yourself
every day because your
mental health is an important
aspect of developing
yourself not only as a person
but as a physician best of
luck to you guys and again
feel free to reach out with
any questions or concerns